[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 [music]
and Japan's invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history of the greatest of
all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price of empire.
It is 1941.
Britain has faced down the threat of
invasion and defeated the Luftwaffe in
the skies over the British Isles.
Now its survival is imperiled by the
longest military campaign [music]
of the Second World War, the Battle of
the Atlantic.
Events in this year in the Balkans in
the Eastern Mediterranean region known
as the Levant
in North and East Africa will decisively
influence the war.
At the end of the year, Japan will take
action that makes the war truly global.
But before that, the story of the Second
World War is to be transformed by a
single word,
Barbarossa.
On the 1st of September 1939, the
passenger liner Athenia left Glasgow
with 1,103
passengers.
On the evening of the 3rd, the day that
Britain declared war, she was sighted by
the German submarine U-30, which fired
two torpedoes.
Athenia sank at 10:40 the next morning.
Interviews with survivors vividly
underline their ordeal.
Between 7:00 and 8:00 we were picked up
by the destroyer.
They took us on board.
98 passengers and 19 crew members were
killed. 54 of the dead were Canadian,
one a 10-year-old girl,
causing Canadian newspapers to chorus in
headlines, "Empire at war."
The Battle of the Atlantic had begun.
It would not properly end until the war
in Europe ended almost 6 years later.
Winston Churchill famously admitted that
the only thing in the war that truly
frightened him was the German U-boat
menace.
The losses were great, but they were not
losses that could knock Britain out of
the war thanks to the countermeasures
that evolved, the escorted convoy
system,
long-range aircraft, and perhaps most
significantly, shipbuilding techniques,
particularly those in American
shipyards, where more ships were being
launched than were being sunk.
At the start of the war, Admiral Karl
Dönitz, chief of the U-boat force, had
claimed that he needed a fleet of 300
vessels, but he only had 58, and U-boat
building was not made a priority until
1942 when Hitler allowed that the
submarine will in the end decide the
outcome of the war.
It did not.
By the end of the war, Germany had 463
[music]
U-boats, but that was too many too late.
The pride of the German Navy, the
Kriegsmarine, was her capital ships, and
the pride of these was the Bismarck.
The steel used in the construction of
the Bismarck
could have built 100 submarines.
Instead, it produced a single battleship
that went to war on May the 19th,
[music] 1941.
She was from [music] the start shadowed
by British naval forces and elements of
the Fleet Air Arm.
She was brought to battle, and after
just 10 days at sea, she was sunk.
>> [music]
>> The Rodney opened fire first,
and shortly afterwards the King George V
did the same.
It was a great tonic after not having
had any breakfast to hear 16-in gun
salvos going off just in front of one.
>> [cheering]
>> By contrast, submarines had been
effective in praying on the crucial
supply routes that brought food and
vital war material to Britain.
Though the impact of these losses had
[music] been softened,
annual imports of food had been reduced
from 55 million to 35 million tons, and
eating and farming habits had been
changed by what was available, what
rationing allowed, and what government
agencies recommended.
Friendly advice leads to
better food, better health, and greater
energy.
Make use of your food advice center.
It's there to help you.
The first of what German U-boat
commanders in the Atlantic called the
happy times lasted until the early
months of '41.
The Germans introduced the pack tactic,
Rudeltaktik, which the British called
the wolf pack.
Groups of U-boats acting together with
the assistance of information from
British naval codes which they had
deciphered.
So great was their initial success that
in March 1941, Winston Churchill [music]
released 40,000 men from military
conscription to work in the dockyards,
where a backlog of 800,000 tons of
damaged shipping was awaiting repair.
The U-boat of the day was not the
stealthy killer of today. It was
diesel-powered on the surface,
battery-powered when submerged when it
traveled as slowly as the slowest cargo
vessel.
The U-boat's vulnerability was found out
by augmented destroyer and corvette
escort groups accompanying convoys.
Where in January and February of 1941 no
U-boats had been lost, they now began to
suffer monthly sinkings.
By war's end, 75% of those who served on
U-boats had been killed,
a casualty rate unequaled by any branch
of any service in any country.
From May, convoys were being escorted
for the entire Atlantic crossing with
the Royal Canadian Navy assuming
responsibility for the western zone.
Just as crucially, the United States,
despite its neutrality,
was escorting convoys as far east as
Iceland.
At the start of 1941, the president of
the United States [music] had sent the
strongest possible signal to his people
that they could not forever stand idly
by.
I say to the democracies, we Americans
are vitally concerned in your defense of
freedom.
It was January the 6th, 1941 and the
State of the Union address.
In his speech, Roosevelt defined the
four freedoms he saw as being
fundamental to people everywhere.
Freedom of speech,
of worship,
from want, and from fear.
In April 1941, a minor event of great
significance influenced to the Battle of
the Atlantic.
The capture of U-boat 110.
Forced to the surface by Royal Navy
action, the boarding party stripped
U-110 of everything portable, including
her code signal codebook and Enigma
machine.
The documents and the machine helped
code breakers at GCHQ,
the British government code and cipher
school at Bletchley Park,
penetrate the 1.253
trillion permutations of the Enigma
code.
Thereafter decrypting more than a
million Kriegsmarine messages during the
war,
the improvement in Allied
countermeasures is demonstrated by the
figures.
In the first 6 months of 1941, about a
million and a half tons of shipping had
been lost to submarines, but that figure
was almost exactly halved
in the second half of the year and at
the cost of 32 U-boats sunk.
By 1943,
the picture had changed dramatically.
In 1943,
U-boats were sunk.
It was to defend other Imperial trade
routes coming to Britain through the Red
Sea and Suez that [music] Britain was
established in Egypt.
It was this that brought war to the
North African shore and this that made
the Horn of Africa of vital interest.
We did about 6 weeks
bush warfare training and maneuvers,
which I thought was really inadequate.
We were in no way trained for war. Half
of the blokes had never fired a rifle.
We had the old 303s from the First World
War.
That's what we were equipped with.
1940,
we went into action.
In late January 1941, Lieutenant General
Sir Alan Cunningham advanced.
Covering 55 km a day, his Indian, South
African, British, and East and West
African [music] troops crossed into
Ethiopia on February the 2nd, 1941.
Their task, to take on the Italians
and put the Emperor Haile Selassie back
on his throne.
In our first battle against the
Italians,
we actually came out on top.
We drove the Italians out.
That number does It is touch and go
whether we're going to succeed [music]
or not.
So, they brought in a few British
regiments
and a brigade of Indian regiments.
The Massawa
is what's into Abyssinia.
And now we had to fight the Italians to
take Abyssinia back to them,
which we did.
Amazingly, we did.
With our clean home army,
we succeeded.
Cunningham had taken 50,000 prisoners
and gained more than 930 sq km at the
cost of 135 men killed and four
captured.
Italian resistance [music]
continued until late November, but by
then, the majority of British troops had
been [music] withdrawn to bolster the
forces facing a more serious challenge
in North Africa.
Vichy France and Franco's Spain, both
sympathetic to the Axis powers, [music]
controlled Morocco.
Algeria was Vichy French, as was
Tunisia.
>> [music]
>> Libya was an Italian possession. Egypt,
which meant control of the Suez Canal,
was a British protectorate.
The Mediterranean was a disputed sea.
When Italy entered the war, Britain had
been obliged [music] to withdraw naval
units from the Asian station,
which left Singapore and Malaya with
fatally little protection.
The Mediterranean Fleet of the Royal
Navy, with several Royal Australian Navy
vessels, intercepted and sunk or
severely [music] damaged several ships
of the Regia Marina, the Italian Navy,
in the Battle of Matapan off the
southwest coast of the Greek
Peloponnesian Peninsula. It was the 27th
and 28th of March and the last fleet
action to [music] be fought by the Royal
Navy.
The conflict in the Mediterranean
invested a small British possession with
great strategic significance.
This was Malta,
a fortress with airfields and an immense
naval dockyard.
Well, that was the 234th raid on the
island and there have been many since
then.
Battered continuously from the air,
supplied by erratic convoy, the
resilience and defiance of the Maltese
people was recognized in 1942 by the
British monarch. The entire island was
awarded the highest civilian decoration
for gallantry, the George Cross. It
appears today on the flag of the
Republic of Malta, independent since the
early 1960s.
Keeping Malta meant keeping open the sea
lanes along which supplies went to the
Allied forces gathering in North Africa.
Malta was through
was supply base.
There were stacks and stacks of
supplies.
Spare parts, petrol,
rations, medical,
and all covered with careless knees.
And that's our first night in the
Western Desert.
The British had begun to press west from
Alexandria against the Italians. By
January the 5th, 1941, Bardia had fallen
to the 6th Australian Division. By the
22nd, Tobruk fell, and on the 6th of
February, the Australians entered
Benghazi.
So, there was a lot of
British armies there
and they'd all the time before we went
there.
After they fed us and we went to sleep
on the ground,
we heard this noise.
>> [clears throat]
[groaning]
>> I said, "What What's that noise?"
He said, "Oh, you'll find out."
The Italian Air Force
Savoyas
and Martins
with a sprinkling of German Focke-Wulfs
and Messerschmitts.
There was so thick
that I couldn't tell what it was.
It's like a black cloud.
The first we had ever [music] seen
over an aerial attack. We'd never seen
one before.
Cuz the Italians had no air force in
East Africa.
The Messerschmitts,
they came in the first machine gunning.
And of course, we started running like
mad men.
The sergeant said, "Settle down. Lie
down. Don't run.
Press to the ground. Just stay there.
By running around, you make yourself a
target.
And these chaps are going to get you,
you know."
And of course, we we lost a few men, of
course, through ignorance.
My god,
we had never experienced [music] that
sort of thing before.
British success in North Africa was
short-lived.
In early January, Churchill had weakened
the force in North Africa by ordering
that troops be sent to reinforce the
campaign in Greece.
And on the day that Benghazi fell,
Hitler, who had announced a month
earlier that he was giving direct
military support to Italy, appointed a
general to command the German contingent
in Libya.
His name was Erwin Rommel.
He made his first move on March the 24th
and pressing forward entered Benghazi
unopposed on April the 4th.
The advance continued at such a pace and
the withdrawal in such confusion that
two British generals, O'Connor and
Neame, were captured and the Australians
were in danger of being cut off.
By the end of April, Tobruk was besieged
and the British had been driven back to
the positions from which they had jumped
off 5 months earlier.
The news for the Allies was equally
bleak in the Balkans.
Hitler, already disturbed by Italy's
failed invasion of Greece, reacted
violently when the new Yugoslav regime,
which had thrown out his ally Prince
Paul, signed a non-aggression pact with
Stalin
and indicated a willingness to discuss a
coalition with Great Britain.
>> [music]
>> The German offensive in the Balkans
opened on April the 6th with a Luftwaffe
attack on the Yugoslav capital,
Belgrade.
50 divisions with strong air support
brushed aside 28 poorly equipped
Yugoslav divisions without air support.
Losing just 151 dead as they marched
through the country on their way to
Greece
to which British and Commonwealth troops
had been sent.
On April the 17th, Yugoslavia
surrendered. The Axis took over 300,000
prisoners, but that was not the end of
the fight.
Nothing in the Balkans is or ever has
been that clear-cut.
The terrain is irregular and complex,
lending itself to guerrilla-style
partisan tactics.
The mixed ethnicities have never
coalesced and rivalries run deep and
destructive.
The area became the only theater for
effective partisan activity, but those
who fought the common enemy, Hitler's
Germany, put just as much energy into
fighting each other. Serbian
monarchists, the Chetniks, could not
agree common cause with Croatian Ustaše
and neither allied with partisans led by
a former agent of the Communist
International who called himself Tito.
The German's callous invasion of Greece,
another black outrage in Hitler's record
of crime, is thus launched over land
where superiority in tanks and motor
transport may avail them nothing.
We didn't have really proper maps. We
only had a few sketches.
And Keir had to me, "Oh, there's a
there's a goat herd over there. Could
you would you like to go over and and
and ask him if he knows where the hell
we are?" He said,
"Uh sir." I said, "Very good, sir."
I walked across and this man was sat
there
and I said, "Excuse me,
do you understand English?" And he
looked at me a bit old-fashioned and
said, "No, but I can speak American."
Most of our tanks we had to destroy
ourselves because we didn't have spares.
I had the last tank on the road just
north of Thebes somewhere.
The engine packed up
and the planes came over and we piled
into a ditch.
And they caught it with a bomb,
took the tracks and it off one side.
And then they ordered him through every
man himself. The Greek government had
collapsed.
So, that was it.
The Greek first army surrendered on
April the 20th and just over a week
later the Royal Navy took off W Force
comprising an Australian division, a New
Zealand division, and a British armored
brigade.
>> [cheering]
>> W Force was evacuated to Crete leaving
10,000 of its number behind as prisoners
of war.
As with Dunkirk, the British had managed
to extricate the men, but had been
obliged to leave behind the heavy
equipment.
The Germans entered Athens on April
27th. 2 days earlier in Führer Directive
28, Hitler had ordered the capture of
Crete.
Before the assault on Crete was
launched, one of the war's most bizarre
footnotes had played out.
It would not appear to have been a time
for the Axis to be seeking peace with
the beleaguered Allies, but someone felt
that they should.
At 17:45 on the 10th of May, 1941,
a specially prepared Me 110 took to the
air.
Its pilot and sole occupant was wearing
a leather flying suit bearing the rank
of captain.
He flew to Scotland, was unable to spot
his destination, and parachuted out of
the plane just after 11:00 at night.
Under questioning, he admitted that he
was Rudolf Hess,
the third most powerful man in the
Reich,
deputy Führer and long-time friend and
confidant of Adolf Hitler.
Yes, I'm the man that captured Rudolf
Hess. I rushed into the house and the
first thing I saw was a man in the
parachute.
He said he was married and pulled out a
photograph of his little boy of whom he
was very proud.
He said, "I have seen him this morning,
but heaven knows when I shall see him
again."
Hess was on a peace mission which
appears to have been entirely his own
idea.
When a furious Hitler learned of it, he
initiated Aktion Hess, a propaganda
effort to denigrate Hess [music] who was
not, of course, empowered to negotiate
for peace.
Imprisoned, Hess took his own life in
1987.
He was 93 years old.
By the time Rudolf Hess was safely in
British custody, the Luftwaffe had
launched its first attacks on the island
of Crete.
After 5 days on May the 20th, the
Germans began their assault.
The plan was for an airborne invasion.
It was a disaster and Germany would
never, as a result, use airborne troops
again.
Glider troops and four of the parachute
battalions were smashed to pieces before
they could join the fight.
By the end of May the 20th, German
forces had failed to secure any of their
objectives. German commanders decided
[music] to throw all available resources
into an attack on Maleme, the location
of the airfield.
On the morning of May 21st, the Germans
advanced and found that the troops
defending the airfield had been
withdrawn.
The Germans wasted no time flying in
reinforcements.
British Army commanders were soon
considering surrender and on the first
anniversary of Dunkirk, British troops
were evacuated leaving the people of
Crete to face well-documented
atrocities.
British British Empire and Dominion
troops were also in action at the
eastern end of the Mediterranean.
Then, as now, a region of great
strategic significance.
The Levant, substantially [music]
the area of modern Iraq, Syria, and
Lebanon, was largely controlled by an
administration loyal to Pétain's [music]
Vichy French government.
On the 8th of June, a British force with
Free French elements advanced into Syria
and Lebanon with the expectation of
meeting token resistance from the Vichy
garrison.
Its expectations were disappointed.
Vichy forces resisted fiercely.
It was not until July the 15th that
resistance was overcome.
38,000 Vichy troops were given the
option of joining the Free French or
being repatriated to France.
Only 5,700
elected to fight on.
The defeat of Italy in Abyssinia and the
Vichy French in the Levant were
important [music] in securing Britain's
position in Egypt as a base for the
battle in North Africa
where fighting had flared again.
It had [music] not favored the Allies.
We got to a place
directly opposite Tobruk.
Place called Sidi Rezegh.
What would you expect to find there?
Nothing.
There was a stone and there was really
nothing.
El Adam,
Bir Burooz, Bardia Pass.
All these names are part of the desert,
but there was nothing there.
Just a pile of stones
with a number on it.
On June 15th, General Wavell,
Commander-in-Chief, succumbing to
pressure from Churchill, who wanted him
to relieve [music] Tobruk, had launched
an offensive, Operation Battleaxe.
Two days later, he had been pushed back
to the start line and the British had
lost more than 90 tanks, casualties of
what was to become one of the most
feared weapons of the ground war, the
German 88-mm anti-tank gun.
I watched the German 88.
It fired six shots and burned up five
tanks.
Churchill was less tolerant of failure
amongst his generals than any other
leader.
His record [music] makes Hitler, as
Hitler was to point out to his
commanders, seem benevolent.
Failure [music] cost Wavell his job and
on July 5th, he was replaced by Claude
Auchinleck, who would enjoy initial
success.
In August, [music] an Allied campaign
had seen British and Soviet troops
working together for the first time
invade and suppress Iran with its
priceless oil reserves.
Though nominally neutral, the Shah of
Iran had shown sympathy for [music] the
Axis cause.
The invasion, Operation Contenance,
deposed him
and opened an overland route along which
the Allies could send supplies to
Russia.
On the 18th of November, a fresh North
African offensive, Crusader, was
launched.
It had been planned by General
Cunningham,
who did not last long.
Rommel reacted swiftly, stopping the
advance and taking a heavy toll of
Allied tanks.
The attempted breakout from Tobruk
failed on the 20th
and on the 24th, Rommel's armor, dashing
for the wire, as it was said, reached
the Egyptian-Libyan frontier.
Cunningham sought permission to halt the
offensive and fall back. Auchinleck, as
his commander, did more than disagree.
He dismissed him.
Fighting in North Africa would resume
decisively in 1942.
But as a battlefield,
it had been quite overshadowed by events
elsewhere.
For two days in August 1941,
the leaders of the great [music]
democracies had met aboard an American
warship in Placentia Bay in
Newfoundland.
It was the first wartime summit between
President Roosevelt and Prime Minister
Churchill.
Although America was not in the war, the
meeting importantly affirmed the
relationship between Britain and the US.
The Atlantic Charter that resulted from
the meeting spelled out eight common
principles: no territorial expansion,
liberalization of world trade, freedom
of the seas, basic standards [music] for
international labor, economic management
and welfare, restoration of
self-government to countries occupied in
the war, and finally, which Churchill
must have known was the death knell of
empire, self-determination for all
peoples.
Such a demonstration of Anglo-American
solidarity
>> [music]
>> was in part a response to increasing
tensions in Asia.
And in part,
it was recognition of the tremendous
escalation of the European war.
On the 22nd of June, 1941,
Germany and her Axis partners had
invaded the Union of Soviet Socialist
Republics.
The legend of Frederick the First is
that he sleeps in a cave from which he
will one day emerge to lead Germany back
to her mythologized greatness.
For his red beard, Frederick is known as
Barbarossa.
Führer Directive 21 of December the
18th, 1940, gave that name to the
instruction that the German armed forces
must be prepared, even before the
conclusion of the war against England,
to crush Soviet Russia in a rapid
campaign.
The Barbarossa plan said that the bulk
of the Russian army stationed in Western
Russia will be destroyed by daring
operations led by deeply penetrating
armored spearheads.
Of course, secrecy was vital.
Germany and the Soviet Union had signed
a non-aggression pact.
Amazingly, the assault by up to 4
million troops, 600,000 vehicles, and
about the same number of horses did come
as a surprise to Stalin.
Despite German violations of Soviet
airspace and warnings, including one
from the anti-Nazi German ambassador to
Moscow, Stalin trusted Hitler.
On June the 22nd, a Soviet forward
position radioed, "We are being fired
on. What are we to do?"
On the day of the invasion, Hitler had
written to his ally, Mussolini.
"Duce," he began, "I am writing this
letter to you at a moment when months of
anxious deliberation and continuous
nerve-racking are ending in the hardest
decision of my life."
But it was, in fact, the one decision to
which his life was utterly committed.
On June the 22nd, he had unleashed Drang
nach Osten, the thrust to the east.
Hitler's objective, the AA line, which
linked Arkhangelsk to Astrakhan, was
about 3,200 km from Berlin.
Three army groups were to advance on
divergent axes. The front line, 2,100 km
at the start, would spread to over 3,000
km as the attack developed.
German divisions were supported by 40
from Axis partners.
Only Romanians and Italians were there
in significant numbers, but there were
Dutch, French, Danish, Croatian,
Slovakian, Hungarian, Romanian,
and even a Spanish division, although
they were not officially at war with
anyone.
Russian forces were found deployed
following every twist and turn of the
border instead of holding a formed
defensive position.
The Red Air Force was similarly forward
and exposed.
1,500 Soviet aircraft were destroyed on
the ground and 300 in the air in the
first 24 hours.
Hitler was almost presented with a
complete victory. Almost.
Only a little over half of the Red
Army's strength was in the west and
exposed to Germany's first assault.
It fell back or fell apart, but
astonishingly
losses were made good and the factories
on which the war effort would depend
were dismantled and shipped to safety.
2,593
industrial units had been transported
[music] east by train to the other side
of the Urals by the end of the year.
Plant and workforce would be back in
action turning out tanks and guns and
aircraft
within days or weeks of arrival. Workers
living where they could and eating in
state canteens that fed 25 million
people every day.
The offensive in the Ukraine resulted in
one of the most complete battlefield
victories in history.
Von Kleist's Panzer Group 1 and
Guderian's Panzer Army closed the trap
around Kiev.
Encircling an army which on the 26th of
September surrendered 655,000
Russian prisoners.
The largest single capture in the
history of warfare.
Well over a million Russians were
prisoners of war by September.
On October the 3rd, Hitler announced
victory.
His propaganda minister, [music] Joseph
Goebbels, put it poetically.
"The eastern continent," he said, "lies
like a limp virgin in the mighty arms of
the German Mars."
The smashing success of the first 3
weeks of Barbarossa had come at a cost
to the Axis.
The strength of armored units had been
reduced by 40% and almost 400,000 troops
were dead, wounded, or missing.
As early as August the 11th, Hitler had
written,
"The whole situation makes it
increasingly plain that we have
underestimated the Russian Colossus."
By mid-October 1941, the Ostheer, the
Eastern Army, had occupied territory
where 45% of the Soviet population
lived.
64% of its coal was mined and 47% of its
grain was harvested.
Germany would remain in occupation of
these bountiful lands until the summer
of 1944
and squander the opportunity.
In many parts of the occupied territory,
the elders, rejoicing in their release
from Soviet oppression, greeted the
invaders with traditional bread and
salt. Observing local joy, Field Marshal
Fedor von Bock, commanding Army Group
Center, observed, "This people would not
be difficult to lead."
But these were Untermenschen, subhuman.
Hitler's crusade was by design genocidal
and his overriding concept was Volk
Krieg,
the clash of peoples.
Hitler could have made an empire, but he
made only enemies.
On September the 30th, General Guderian
had begun to move on Moscow. All other
units along a wide front moving on
October 2nd. Today, Hitler said, "Began
the last great offensive of the war."
But on October the 8th, rain fell.
It was what the Russians called
rasputitsa,
internal seas, the time when roads
dissolve.
Fierce fighting continued, but the
armies literally got bogged down and the
offensive stalled.
Leading German units were within 30 km
of Moscow.
The Germans along an 1,800 km front had
much of European Russia in their hands.
Soviet reinforcements were found.
Resistance was desperate.
Moscow did not fall.
Hitler was right.
He had underestimated the [music]
Russian Colossus.
Between June and December 1941, for
every dead German there were 20 dead
Soviets.
But like Charles the 12th of Sweden who
was undone at Poltava in 1709, like
Napoleon who took Moscow before being
forced into a disastrous retreat in
1812,
Adolf Hitler had mightily wounded the
Russian bear,
but he had not killed it.
>> [cheering]
>> Operation Barbarossa was over.
What would happen next?
What happened when fighting resumed with
Zhukov's counteroffensive in December
was part of a very different war.
Because on the 7th of December, as
Zhukov's offensive was starting to bite,
Japan thrust itself into the conflict
with surprise attacks on several fronts,
including the one that led Franklin D.
Roosevelt to term December the 7th
a date which will live
in infamy.